<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Protection perswading subjection: or A [brace] word of peace to the well-affected. Caveat to the contentious. Rod for the rebellious. In three positions proving His Highness 1 To be the aptest, ablest and most worthy person for place of Lord Protector. 2. That the people, by the laws of God and man are obliged to loyalty and obedience to his Highness. 3. That all opposers are enemies to the publick peace and safety, and deserve exemplary punishment. By E.M. Esq; a cordial well-willer to the tranquillity and safety of this Commonwealth.</title>
            <author>E. M., Esq.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 57KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A89127</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863000</idno>
  <idno type="VID">115181</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2248547292</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing M20</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E729_4</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R202840</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863000</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99863000e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A89127)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 115181)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 112:E729[4])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Protection perswading subjection: or A [brace] word of peace to the well-affected. Caveat to the contentious. Rod for the rebellious. In three positions proving His Highness 1 To be the aptest, ablest and most worthy person for place of Lord Protector. 2. That the people, by the laws of God and man are obliged to loyalty and obedience to his Highness. 3. That all opposers are enemies to the publick peace and safety, and deserve exemplary punishment. By E.M. Esq; a cordial well-willer to the tranquillity and safety of this Commonwealth.</title>
                  <author>E. M., Esq.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 30 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Henry Hills living in Py-corner,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1653. [i.e. 1654]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The words "Word of .. rebellious." are bracketed together on title page.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Feb: 13:".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Cromwell, Oliver, 1599-1658 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-06 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-06 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:115181:1"/>
            <p>PROTECTION PERSWADING SUBJECTION: OR A Word of Peace to the well-affected. Caveat to the Contentious. Rod for the Rebellious.</p>
            <p>In three POSITIONS proving His Highness
<list>
                  <item>1 To be the aptest, ablest and most worthy person for place of Lord PROTECTOR.</item>
                  <item>2. That the People, by the Laws of God and man are obliged to Loyalty and Obedience to his Highness.</item>
                  <item>3. That all Opposers are Enemies to the publick Peace and Safety, and deserve exemplary punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>E. M.</hi> Esq A cordial well-willer to the tranquillity and safety of this Commonwealth.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Pray for the peace of Jerusalem: let them prosper that love thee,</p>
               <bibl>Psalm 122. 6.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>—And there followed him a Band of men, whose hearts God had touched. But the children of Belial said, How shall this man save us? and they despised him, and brought him no presents: but he held his peace,</p>
               <bibl>1 Sam. 26, 27.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>Henry Hills</hi> living in <hi>Py-corner,</hi> 1653.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:115181:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:115181:2"/>
            <head>Three Positions, principally tending to the present and future preservation of the peace, safety, and prosperity of the three Nations, <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> proved by Reasons, Authorities, Examples, Divine, Moral, Political.</head>
            <argument>
               <p n="1">1. That His Highness, <hi>Oliver,</hi> Lord Protector of this Common-wealth, under God, is the most apt, able, and best deserving person for that High and Honourable Title, Place, and Calling.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That the people of this Commonwealth, by the Laws of God, are obliged with all fidelity and reverence to yield all ready and willing obedience to His Highness, as their Chief Magistrate un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der God, and to submit to this present Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That whosoever resisteth or opposeth his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, and the present Government, is a transgres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sor of Gods Ordinances, and the Laws of the Land, An Enemy to the peace, safety, and pros<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perity of this Commonwealth, and deserves ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplary punishment.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>TO begin with the first position. If we ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve the History of Holy Writ, we may find a twofold way to Honour: Direct, when
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:115181:3"/> God calls; Indirect, when man by sinister means seeks it, without the Lords warrant. <hi>David</hi> went the first; and his Crown departed not from his head, till nature had paid her debt, and his life dissolved; neither did his Honour expire with his Breath, nor his greatness go into the Grave with him, but when he is gone, his issue succeeds him. <hi>Absalom</hi> his Rebellious Son went the other way, and sought to pull down his Religious Father whom the Lord had set up, but his sins pulld him down with vengeance, only a dumb pillar speaks his unhappy memory. High Seats of Honour are slippery places: yet being placed by an Almighty hand, whom the Lord sets there, he can keep secure. If we look as well to the way, as the thing, we shall find, The safest path to lasting preferment, is that, which (with a divine call) vertue treads: which was well no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the Antient <hi>Romans,</hi> when they built the Temple of Honour so, that none could enter it, <hi>(ni prius pertransiverunt Templum Virtutis)</hi> but they must first pass through that of Vertue. And certainly if with an equal and impartial eye we shall look upon the whole course of His Highness wise and vertuous deportment, in all affairs both Civil and Martial, we cannot but confess, he hath most truly trode that path, which leads to lasting Honor, and is, in several Respects, the most fit and proper person for that most Honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Title, and place of Lord Protector.</p>
            <p>First, in respect his Highness is, perfectly in all points, such a person as the Lord by his Servant <hi>Moses</hi> specially directed to be elected as Chief Magistrate, King, or Ruler over his people the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:115181:3"/> Children of <hi>Israel,</hi> Deut. 17. 15. <hi>Thou shalt make him King, Ruler, or Governour over thee, whom the Lord shall choose: From among thy Brethren shalt thou make thee a King or Governour over thee: Thou shalt not set a stranger over thee, that is not thy Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi> In the first place, God is to choose, then the people to accept of, elect and create, him whom God hath chosen their Governour; when God hath chosen, the people ought not to deny or refuse him, for the precept is strict and speci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, <hi>Thou shalt make him King whom the Lord shall choose:</hi> So that if the Lord shall choose and send to his people a careful, vigilant, pious, Protector, they ought with all loyalty not onely to respect and honour him, but also with all reverence and love to affect, serve and obey him, whereof more hereafter.</p>
            <p>Now to prove that his Highness is a person chosen of God to this place of Protector, his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Word, which is his revealed will, by several Texts of infallible truth doth evidently demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strate. Protector, as it is a place of preheminence, so it is a Title that intimates a Superiour power in the person there with honoured and advanced. And <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. 1. We have an express Text, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving this point, <hi>There is no power but of God, the powers that be are ordained of God,</hi> Whereby it is apparent that this power wherewith his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness is invested, is ordained of God, and that our Protector is chosen, called, sent and set in this high Seat of Honour by Gods Ordinance, yea by God himself, which if we will believe the Lord himself, is not to be disputed: For saith God, <hi>By me Kings reign, and Princes bear rule, and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:115181:4"/> Rulers have Dominion.</hi> God is the King of Kings, Lord of Lords, the Primitive of all principali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and from him all authority is derived. He alone disposeth of all Honours, Dignities, and Promotions. The shields of the Earth belong to the Lord, <hi>Psal.</hi> 47. 3, 7, 9. Rulers receive all their power from, and have their whole depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance on Gods divine power, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 23. 7, 8, &amp;c. <hi>Hannahs</hi> Hymn, Speak no more presumptuously, Let not arrogancy come out of your mouth: for <note place="margin">He looseth the colar of Kings, leadeth away Princes as a prey, &amp;c. Job 12. 14 18, 19, 21. Psal. 113. 7, 8.</note> the Lord is a God of Knowledge, and by him enterprizes are established. He maketh poor and he maketh rich, bringeth low and exalteth. He raiseth the poor out of the dust, &amp;c. to set them among Princes, and to make them inherit the seat of glory: for the pillars of the Earth are the Lords, and he hath set the world upon them. And to the same purpose, <hi>Psal.</hi> 75. Though the Earth and the inhabitants thereof be dissolved (all things be out of Order) yet I (saith the Lord) will establish the Pillars thereof. And in the next ensuing verses ill affected persons are warn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not to set themselves against such as the Lord sets up to be Governours, stiling them foolish and wicked that so do. I said to the foolish, be not so foolish, and to the wicked, lift not up the horn, neither speak with a stiff neck: for to <note place="margin">Psa. 76. 3. 5. 12.</note> come to preferment, is neither from the East, &amp;c. But God is the Judge, he maketh low, and he maketh high. Agreeable to that place, <hi>Eccle.</hi> 4. For out of the Prison he commeth to reign; when as he that is born in his Kingdom is made poor; according to which is the Confession of the Prophetical King, and Kingly Prophet <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:115181:4"/> who by experience had found the truth thereof, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 29. Thine O Lord is greatness and power, and glory, and victory, and praise: for all that is in heaven, and in earth is thine; thine is the Kingdom, O Lord, and thou excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lest <note place="margin">Because thou hast cast away the word of the Lord, the Lord hath cast thee away from being King, and hath rent away the Kingdom from thee, and given it to thy Neighbour that is better than thee, said <hi>Samuel</hi> to <hi>Saul, 1 Sam.</hi> 15. 25, 26, 28.</note> as head over all; Both riches and Honour come of thee, and thou reignest over all, and in thine hand is power and strength, and in thine hand it is to make great, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again, for a further proof of this point, by rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal consequence upon cleer Argument, <hi>à minori ad majus,</hi> we cannot but necessarily conclude, that by divine Grace and Providence his Highness is made Lord Protector of these three Nations. Are all the hairs of our heads numbered? and shall not a sparrow fall on the ground without our Heavenly Father? <hi>Mat.</hi> 10. 29, 30. (matters in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>considerable and of no moment) &amp; can we ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine the conquest of three potent Kingdoms hath been accomplished, and the Conqueror become the Protector thereof, and these great things not done by divine Providence? Far be it from the belief of all Holy-hearted men, to attribute the effecting hereof to Human powers or policies, (but onely as externally conducing thereunto) or to ascribe ought herein to the Fortune of War. Such conceits are meer <hi>Nugae,</hi> fond and phan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tastical fictions of Heathenish worldlings Imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation. <hi>Ignorantia causarum confinxit Fortunam.</hi> Ignorance made Fortune a Goddess: we must not rob God of his glory to give it to a feigned Deity. <hi>Quod sapientibus et piis singularis dei pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>videntia
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:115181:5"/> est, id insipientibus et prophanis fortuna dicitur,</hi> What the wise and pious call Providence, foolish and prophane persons term Fortune: we as good Christians ought and must maintain his Highness, <hi>Dei gratia et providentia Divina,</hi> by the grace of God, and divine providence, to be Lord Protector of the three nations.</p>
            <p>Then in the second Respect, his Highness is a most fit person to be our Protector, according to that Divine Direction, <hi>Deut.</hi> 17. 15. From a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong thy Brethren, thou shalt make a King or Ruler over thee. Here is a special precept in the Affirmative; He must be a native Born, one of thy Brethren, that thou make Governour over thee; And then a strong prohibition in the Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative, Thou shalt not set a stranger over thee: By this Divine rule then, we ought not to admit of a Forein Ruler or Governour over us. God hath chosen, and we according to his said di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection from among our Brethren have made a Protector over us, whom God protect, and let his Highness prosper, and all such perish, as pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose or indeavour to disturb the publique peace of this Commonwealth, by attempting to set up any Alien, Stranger, Foreiner or other, contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the Rule of Gods word and his Ordinance. Again, his Highness is our Brother in another spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial relation and respect: not only <hi>Natione,</hi> by a national fraternity, but also <hi>fidei relatione,</hi> by a spiritual kind of relation of faith, our Brother not only <hi>Regione,</hi> but also <hi>Religione,</hi> not by Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion or Countrey onely, but by Religion also, a Christian, not Antichristian Brother; Our Brother in Christ, a Brother in the neerest rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:115181:5"/> that can be, even a fellow Member of that <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Theodosius</hi> the Emperor held it to be no less honour to be <hi>Membrum Christi,</hi> than <hi>Caput Imperii.</hi>
               </note> Body whereof Christ Jesus is the head; not of that Society, Body or assembly whereof <hi>Papa est Ecclesiae Caput,</hi> Antichrist usurps the title of head of the Church: and in this respect of Religious Fraternity, we owe to his Highness most loyall Allegeance as our Liege Soveraign Protector, to defend our lives, Liberties, Estates, and Lawes, but principally our Religion, which is most pretious, by how much the spiritual and eternal welfare of our souls is to be preferred be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Our Temporal Estate, and the Transitory triflles of this vale of misery.</p>
            <p>The next thing to be proved is, That his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness is the most able person for the place of Lord Protector of this Commonwealth.</p>
            <p>To give a perfect account of his Highness wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy and most illustrious abilities, is a weighty work, requiring an able wit, a learned pen, and a larger volume, than at present is intended, this Treatise consisting but of short hints and heads, which (by divine permission and assistance) may be amplified hereafter, and others in the Interim may be put in mind to contribute their endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours for performance of some more exquisite peece on the same subject: It being a work of that worth and weight, that the best and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blest pens and pates of our age need not disdain to make it their Master-piece.</p>
            <p>For without all Question, The Lords hand hath been exceeding large in transcendent rich Gifts and Graces, rare and royal indowments towards his Highness; Giving him the heart of <hi>David,</hi> the head of <hi>Solomon,</hi> the hands of <hi>Joshua,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:115181:6"/> Gideon, Sampson.</hi> His vertue, wisdom, valour, (three sure foundations on which a worthy Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour ought to be built) have most illustriously appeared in the whole progress of his happy proceedings in all affairs both Civil and Martial, of State and War.</p>
            <p>The large Series of his many Successful victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries are certain evidences of his wisedom and valour, vertue and piety (which hath indeed the promise of protection and prosperity) and shew us as it were a divine presence walking along with him in all his waies.</p>
            <p>And surely there is much reason, why with a treble respect, we should reverence our Tresno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and prosperous Protector, a person owned and honoured by Heaven: who in the shatter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing shocks of a twice seven years sharp and bloody war, hath stood unshaken (when every minute death (which seldom or never makes distinction by respect of persons) seemed to pass by and shun his sacred person) as one that the Supreme God had in an special manner cared for and secured, one whom the hand of heaven had sheltered, and by a particular guard defended even in the hail of death: The Lord seeming to preserve his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse on purpose to be a present Protector to his people, and a pious promoter of Gods glory hereafter. So that he may truly say with the sweet singer of Israel, <hi>The Lord hath given me the Shield of his salvation, set me in high places, sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued the people that rose against me, under me, and hath preserved me to be the head over Nations.</hi> 2 Sa 22. 34, 36, 44.</p>
            <p>Next to his Highness piety and vertue, the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:115181:6"/> surest foundations of Honour, and lasting Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, let us observe his excellent wisdom and counsel, which hath most eminently been evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denced in compassing so many incomparable Conquests, some without, yea contrary to the advise of his Council of War (though prudent and valiant) some with loss of little blood; which, of all Victories, the <hi>Romans</hi> (in feats of Arms a people most renowned) reputed those the best, which were stained with the least blood: They were content <hi>Camillus</hi> should triumph when <note place="margin">Better is wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom than strength, than weapons of war, <hi>Eccles</hi> 9. 16, 18.</note> he had not fought. And certainly Politique Contrivances of this kind, in these times, are not only commendable and honourable, but espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially requisite, since <hi>virtus an dolus quis in hoste requirit?</hi> Stratagems and advantages are of more use than temerary strength, and the open <note place="margin">Vis Consilii Expers, mole ruit sua.</note> daring valour. Besides this also, the prudent, and discreet, ordering, disciplining, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naging of so great and numerous an Army, dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed into so many several parts of the several Nations, under his Highness Command, is no mean, ordinary, or easie matter: but a most re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable point, and part, of a large and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding heart, repleat with profound Wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and judgement, arguing a vast unfathom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed apprehension, attended with most vigilant circumspection.</p>
            <p>And whereas the life of a Souldier is upon many emergencies, tempting to exorbitancy, many being of the common sort pressed as the refuse and burden of the Land, whom extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gancies, and the desperate face of blood (their course of life being but as it were an ordered
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:115181:7"/> quarrel raised to the fewd of killing) might have hardned to dissolute lewdness and outrages, and made such as those, whom <hi>Lucan</hi> seems to be so much out of charity with, when he complains thus,</p>
            <q>
               <l>Nulla fides pietasque viris, qui castra sequntur,</l>
               <l>Venalesque manus; ibi fas, ubi Maxima merces.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Whereas Souldiers (I say) have been formerly branded with obloquies of debauched behavior, rude rapines, unjust violences, and other vile crimes, as great sinners (whereof some of those of the adverse party have been truly tax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as too guilty) The whole Army under his then Excellencyes command as General, by his Godly precepts, and good examples, with the help of heaven, for the greater and better part is become, and truly termd, an Army of Saints: fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing the paths of their pious leader, observing the directions of our Blessed Saviour; Doing or offering injury or violence to none, content with their pay, devout in their discourse and communication, righteous, sober, and godly in their conversation, yet in courage undaunted, and in the Lords battails alwaies victorious, van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quishing their and our most proud and potent Adversaries,</p>
            <p>And as touching his Highness fortitude, it is surpassing the expression of a weak pen, being for valour invincible, for courage unconquer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, for magnanimity matchless: terrified nor daunted neither with the number nor nature, multitude nor power of men or matters how difficult or dangerous soever they seemed to be, and which, to his Highness eternal honor, ought
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:115181:7"/> to be recorded, as <hi>Cicero</hi> reports of <hi>Caesar,</hi> In all his Commands of the Field, there hath not been found an <hi>Ite,</hi> but a <hi>venite;</hi> as if in all his on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sets, he scorned to be any thing but still a leader, alwaies teaching by strongest Authority, his own forwardness, his own Examples.</p>
            <p>Vertue, Wisdome, Valour wherewith his Highness is compleatly furnished, are tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scendent excellencies; surely there is more di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity in them than we are aware of. Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue with Wisdom, Goodness with Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, <note place="margin">Pro. 2. 7. unto the 15. The Lord preser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth the state of the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, he is a shield to them &amp;c.</note> bring and continue felicity and stability both to Governours and Government, without these, neither can lastingly remain safe and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py: Therefore the holy Ghost by the Prophet <hi>David,</hi> whom God raised from a Shepheard to rule his chosen Inheritance, specially presseth Rulers and Princes to learn lessons of piety and prudence, <hi>Psal. 2. Et nunc Reges intelligite, eru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dimini qui judicatis terram, Servite Domino in ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more, et exultate ei cum tremore: Apprehendite dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciplinam, ne quando irascatur dominus, et perea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis de via justa.</hi> Be wise therefore now O ye Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, be learned yee Judges of the earth; Serve the Lord in fear, and rejoice in trembling, kisse the Son, lest he be angry, and ye perish in the way, &amp;c. lest when ye sing <hi>requiems</hi> to your souls, seem to sleep in the lap of peace and security, when ye are in the midway of your purposes, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction come suddenly, unexpectedly, like a whirlwind, <hi>Proverbs</hi> 1. 27.</p>
            <p>Many and blessed are the fruits of those rich Gifts and Graces, vertue and wisdom. wherwith the Giver of every good and perfect gift hath in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:115181:8"/> and dignifyed our Lord Protector, for which we are obliged to magnify the Almighty who hath so gratiously dealt with us, in giving us such a Governour, and with his Authority, hath vouchsafed him such Abilities, and to give all due honour and reverence to his Highness as Gods immediate Vice-gerent, sent, supplied, and furnished with such compleat endowments suitable and convenient for so high a calling. How sadly doth <hi>Solomon</hi> in his Sermons against the vanities of this vale of misery, pronounce a Wo to that Land, whose King is a Child? <hi>Vae tibi terra, cujus Rex puer est, et cujus principes mane comedunt,</hi> whose Ruler is without wisdom and counsel, and whose Princes are given more to their lusts and pleasure, than the peace, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit and safety of the Commonwealth. Again, in the next verse, how doth he publish and praise the happiness of that nation or people who have a Prince, a Ruler, a Protector, enobled with vertue and wisdom, and the gifts of God? as the marginall notes on the 17. verse render it, <hi>Beata terra cujus Rex nobilis est,</hi> &amp;c. Blessed art thou O land, when thy King or Ruler is the Son of Nobles, &amp;c. upon which text, if any out of his malevolent disposition, or malignity of spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, should shew so much ignorance and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudence, as presume to object ought falsly and wickedly (for truly and on sound grounds none can) against the Honour and nobility of his Highness our present Protector, which I hope none will be so vile and vain to do, let that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son whatere he be, know, that by both divine and humane Herauldry his Highness true Nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:115181:8"/> will be maintained, maugre the might and malice of the most malignant opposers, upon any ground it dare to be denyed: First for No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility of birth, tis well known he is descended from an antient Noble Family: but alas that is the least part of nobleness, and at best but a borrowed honour,</p>
            <q>
               <l>Nam Genus, et proavos, et quae non fecimus ipsi,</l>
               <l>Vix ea nostra voco.</l>
            </q>
            <p>To Boast of noble descent without noble de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sert, is but a vain-glorious bubble. <hi>Melius est prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarè institui, nam bene nasci.</hi> To brag of the antiquity of family, without a real proper merit in the person that would raise a building of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and intitle himself thereto, is to lay a san<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy foundation, which will leave his honour at last in the dust: This is but a shadow, a super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficies, and shell; The Substance, the Quintes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence, the kernel, is Vertue, the firmest Rock whereon to lay the foundation of true nobility <hi>Nobilitas sola est atque uniea virtus.</hi> Bad greatness what is it but the vigor of vice, having both mind and means to be uncontroulably lewd? Whereas Vertue in a man of obscure parentage or low fortune, is like an unpolisht Diamond, lying in the way among Pebles; which however it be neglected of the uncivil vulgar, yet the wise La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pidary takes it up as a Jewel invaluable; it being so much the more glorious, by how much the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther were baser.</p>
            <p>And if it be true, as most certain it is, That Fortitude is the Fountain of Honour, and the highest Nobility had its original rise from Feats of Arms, and that is the great estand most glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:115181:9"/> which hath been gained in the Field; we cannot but grant that the Lord of Hosts hath honoured his Highness with as many or more gallant and glorious Atchievements in Martial Exploits, than ever we find or read of any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son or Prince of this Nation; And therefore we may justly conclude, upon these premisses, his Highness to be inferiour to none of his predeces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sours in this place, in true and real nobility: And for his vertue, wisdom, piety, prudence, va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, policy, power, and all worthy parts, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitting so high a calling, the most apt and able, under the Almighty, that hath so ordained it, to be made the Chief Magistrate, and Protector of this Commonwealth of the three Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
            <p>His Highness aptness and abilities being before but briefly touched, and in some part by a weak pen expressed, It followes that the third part of this position (which is his Highness best deserv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of this place of Honour be also proved, for which purpose, what hath been said before, to all men of unbyassed Judgements might have suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficed; yet in regard his Highness merits are a large field for the best understandings to walk in, and contain matter of weighty moment, and (as far as we may) to stop the mouth of calumny and malignity, Let us consider his many and manifold noble and unparalleld performances, both at home and abroad, (which have been and still are like to be effected, for the safety, peace and prosperity of this Commonwealth) And we cannot but with confidence and constancy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude and maintain, that never any Prince of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:115181:9"/> this Nation, better deserved the place, title and office of Chief Ruler, Governour and Protector, than his now Higness justly doth merit to possess and enjoy the same high Seat of honor. Whom God hath enabled most piously and potently to protect these Nations from domestique, Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stine injuries and insurrections, and from forein Invasions, and govern them with wisdom, coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sel and strength, certainly best deserves the name and place of Lord Protector; but without all controversie God hath given his Highness the best ability so to do; Therefore his Highness is most worthy of the place and title of Protector. The Major of this Syllogism is infallible Truth, The Minor is by reason and known experience evidently demonstrated; Then none but foolish, false, and wicked persons will contradict the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clusion.</p>
            <p>Let us without finister prejudicate apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions observe the whole course of his Highness proceedings and passages. Hath not the Lord made him a <hi>Moses</hi> to us in many respects? First in his humility of Spirit, meekness and mildnes, in patient and Gentle passing by the Ignomy of some ignorant wretches, the opprobrious oblo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quies of some obstinate opposers, carpers and cavillers against the place and honour given to him by the sole disposer of all dignities; rather pittying their weakness than punishing their frenzied folly and wickedness: Therein (for his greater glory) shewing his wisdom (according to <hi>Solomons</hi> philosophy) A wisemans Glory is to passe by an offence: herein also expressing his noble discretion, which is <hi>Auriga virtutum</hi> (as
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:115181:10"/> Saint <hi>Augustine</hi> terms it) the Guide, Moderator, and wise Orderer of all humane passions and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections: As also the generositie of his noble spirit as it were scorning to return the rod of pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishment for every abuse; knowing some to be such as require nothing but neglect to kill them, nothing but a noble not caring disdain and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt to stiffle and destroy them. A Fool strook <hi>Cato</hi> in the Bath, and when he said he was sorry, <hi>Cato</hi> had forgot it; For saies <hi>Seneca, Melius pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tavit ignoscere, quam agnoscere.</hi> Pitty, though a downy vertue, never shines more brightly, than when tis clad in steel. Courage with Compassi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on are sweet Cohabitants. Not such pitty (as our <hi>English</hi> proverb saies) which spoils a City can be praise worthy; But pitty so placed with pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, clemency so conjoined with severity, Mercy so mixed with Justice, as to pardon the penitent, but restrain, punish, and keep under the rebellions and obstinate,</p>
            <q>Parcere subjectis, sed debellare superbos.</q>
            <p>Benefits which in themselves are good, are often made ill, by their misplacing. Severity should be such: <hi>Ʋt poena ad Paucos, metus ad omnes perve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niat,</hi> to punish a few, for preventing the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of many. Let mercy be shewed to the wicked, yet (the prophet tels us) he will not repent. For a person of honour and power to permit publique affronts, reflecting disgrace on his authority and place, to pass without ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplary punishment, may prove very prejudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial, and perillous in several respects. <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>. By obstructing the course of Justice against impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and insolent Malefactors, then by imbold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:115181:10"/> others ill affected to the like saucy and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sufferable presumption. Because sentence (saith <hi>Solomon,</hi> Eccles. 8.) is not executed speedily a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst <note place="margin">Eccl. 8. 11. 17.</note> an evil work, therefore the heart of the Children of men is fully set in them to do evil. Such pitty wounds the publique: which is of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten revenged by those we bestow it upon. The Offenders which we save in this kind, will, if they can, condemn us. <hi>Cicero</hi> is said to be slain by one, whom, being accused of paricide, his Oratory had desended, and procured to be spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. Contemners of Authority in a Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, a body Politick, are like corrupt mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers in the natural body, ought to be cured, or cut off, lest they poison and infect the sound parts. <hi>Moses,</hi> though the mirrour of meekness, Calls to heaven for a miraculous reward of ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance on <hi>Corah</hi> and his Company: <hi>David,</hi> though a man after Gods heart, would not have revi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, cursing <hi>Shimei,</hi> counted Innocent, nor his hoar head go to the grave in peace, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 2. 9.</p>
            <p>Again, in another Respect, Hath not God made his Highnesse a <hi>Moses</hi> to us, in might as well as mildness? a wise and worthy Leader and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverer, to bring us out of <hi>Egyptian slavery,</hi> and the house of bondage, under cruel hard-hearted <hi>Pharaohs</hi> that knew not <hi>Joseph</hi> (that would not know nor give respect to Gods people, for whose sake chiefly God Gives prosperity to a Nation) that despised the cry of the true <hi>Israelites,</hi> gron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing under the heavy oppression of ungodly Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants, and their merciless Task-Masters? A <hi>Moses</hi> to guide and lead us, through a danger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:115181:11"/> wilderness of war, wo, and wretchednesse, where were fierce and fiery Serpents, ready and bent to ruin and destroy us, debauched, despe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, <hi>Atheists, Papists,</hi> and a cursed Crew of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther lewd Miscreants? A <hi>Moses</hi> to lead us secure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by the waters of <hi>Marah</hi> &amp; <hi>Meribah,</hi> bitter strife and deadly division, through a deluge of Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stine dissention, and a red Sea of Blood, (we being saved, whilest our pursuing enemies were swallowed up in those waves they sought to sink us) into our <hi>Canaan</hi> of comfort, flowing with the milk and honey of plenty and peace; the free injoyment of our fundamental, antient and native Lawes, Liberties, Rights, Properties, and Estates; so that we may safely sit under our own Vines and Figtrees, and quietly enjoy that which is, or should be, the chief joy of Hearts, more pretious than all sublunary comforts, our Religion, in the purity and sincerity thereof, cleansed and cleared from the <hi>Egyptian</hi> darkness of Superstitious Errors, Heresies, Idolatrous, Blasphemous, Popish, and Atheistical doctrines, and Traditions of men and Devils, the thick Mists and Clouds, which would choke, obscure and ecclipse the glorious Sun of truth, and light of the Gospel of the Sun of Righteousnes: And so that we may also enjoy the benefit of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon lawes of this Land in the just and upright practice thereof, purged from those gross cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions, exactions and extortions in fees of Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices and Officers, undue, indirect, illegal and unjust proceedings too frequently used, whereby the freeborn people of this Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth are and have been much abused, and the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:115181:11"/> Lawes which in themselves are irreproveably good, are traduced?</p>
            <p>But to proceed in the demonstration of his Highness Worthiness: Hath not the Lord made our Protector a <hi>Joshua</hi> unto this Commonwealth, <hi>filling him with the spirit of wisdom</hi> &amp; <hi>valour,</hi> so that in all his great undertakings, he hath proved vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorious, saving us from the dangers of Dome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stique Insurrections, and Forein Invasions? Hath the Lord been so good and gratious to us in these terrible, doubtful, and desperate times, when we are beset with enemies on all sides, not onely forein profest Foes, but also close, crafty, sly and subtle Serpents in our bosom, deceitful Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versaries lurking in the Bowels of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, because we should not be discouraged for lack of a valiant Captain, nor be as sheep scattered without a shepheard, to be torn and devoured by ravening and rapacious wolves, as to send us a powerful Protector to prevent our ruin? and shall not we be grateful to God the Giver, and acknowledge the true worth of such a good and pretious gift? Hath the Lord been so mindful of us, and so merciful to us, as to raise us up a Ruler and Defender from among our Brethren, most apt, most able, and of the Lords ordaining? and shall not we acknowledge him to be the best deserving person, and most worthy of the Place and Honour of Protec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor?</p>
            <p>And because that this one Chief Ruler should be confirmed in this Calling, and that we should have none occasion to doubt, distrust, grudge or murmur, as though his Highnesse were not sent,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:115181:12"/> and approved of God, hath not the Lord ador<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned his Highness with excellent Gifts and Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, both to Govern the Commonwealth with counsel and wisdom, and to defend it with pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and strength; so that nothing is lacking which belongeth to an illustrious General, or pious and prudent Protector, and Vice-gerent of the Lord, over his people, to make his Highness feared abroad, and honoured at home? And can our thoughts fix upon any other so well deserving this Seat of Honour as his Highness our present Lord Protector? <hi>Si Salus populi sit Suprema lex,</hi> If the peoples safety be the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme law, Certainly this Supreme power doth most justly, legally, and of right belong to his Highnesse, we being beholding, and bound to none (under God) so much as to his Highnesse for the safety and preservation of the lawes and liberties of the three Nations from imminent ruin, how constant and indefatigable hath his Highness been in all indeavors? how vigilant and valiant amidst infinite dangers, and almost invin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible difficulties; ventring cōtinually in all places and upon all occasions his own noble person, to preserve our laws, our lives, our liberties, and our estates, and whatsoever else is or was most near or dear unto us? The Lord hath made his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse really and in truth our Protector; how can it be then, but that the name and place of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector, must most justly belong unto his renown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed person? Hath not the Lord made his Highness (under his own omnipotent Majesty) against our proudest and most potent Adversaries and opposers, whether by Sea or Land, a true and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:115181:12"/> Protector to us? Giving us by his Highness prowess the necks of our Enemies that rose up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst us. Enabling him by matchless might to reduce and conquer the Rebellious Revolters of this Nation; to rout and ruin the bloody <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rish</hi> Rebels; to scourge and subdue the subtle, false, and trayterous <hi>Scots;</hi> to batter, shatter, and scatter the <hi>Hogen Mogen Hollanders</hi> Fleet so at Sea, that in submissive way they humbly sue for peace and Compliance: sparing no pains, spending his noble spirits, imploying his strength, all the powers and faculties of Body and Mind, to procure our peace, safety and prosperity; and prevent the cunning plots and practises, of our Adversaries, which might occasion our trouble, Adversitie and ruin. Such success as the Lord promised to <hi>Joshua,</hi> and the children of <hi>Israel, Joshua</hi> 1. hath the Lord vouchsafed to his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, and the valiant Army under his command; Every place whereon the soles of their feet did tread, hath the Lord given him. There hath not been a man able to stand before his power: So that that victorious <hi>Motto, veni, vidi, vici,</hi> may most properly be applyed to his Highness expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditious Conquests; wherever he comes he over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes. All our Chronicles cannot produce the like president of any person, Potentate or Prince in these Nations, of such unparalleld prowess and prosperity in feats of Arms, and of such worth and wisdome in all Affairs, both Civil and Martial: using such valour and vigilancy to compass those many incomparable Conquests; with a Royal heart resolving to win and wear that most excellent <hi>Motto,</hi> which well becomes
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:115181:13"/> the Atchievements of an Invincible Spirit, <hi>Non Juvat ex facili lecta Corona jugo;</hi> so that we may truly say of his Highness for his <hi>wisdom</hi> &amp; <hi>valour,</hi> as <hi>Samuel</hi> at the election of <hi>Saul</hi> to be King, in another sense, of his corporal height, said, 1 <hi>Sa.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 10. 24.</note> 10. See ye not him whom the Lord hath chosen, that there is none like him among all the people? and all the people shouted and said, God save the King, <hi>Certe videtis, quem Elegit Dominus, quoniam non sit similis illi in omni populo, &amp;c.</hi> None like him among all the people: we may most truly say, aver and avouch, there was none like him among all the preceding Princes of our Nation, for piety, prudence, wisdom, valour, policy, power and prosperity.</p>
            <p>The first Position being proved, It rests that proceeding be made to proof of the second Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sition, which is, That power and preheminence being by Divine Providence given to our Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector, The people of this Commonwealth ought to render willing and ready subjection and obedience to his Highnesse, and by the Lawes of God, and this Land, are bound so to do with all fidelity and reverence.</p>
            <p>If we observe, we may find two things to be the true causes of a publique prosperity in all Nations: Good Government, and Good Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience. A good Magistrate over a perverse peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, is a sound head on a surfetted body; A good Commonalty, and a bad Ruler, is a health<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full body, with an aking head: either bad, are occasions of ruin; both sound, preservatives. A good Governour is a skilful Ship-Master, that takes the shortest, and the safest course, and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:115181:13"/> continually so steers, as the rocks and shelves, which might shipwrack the State, be avoided, and the voyage ever made, with the soonest speed, best profit, most ease. If the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth be obedient, and the Ruler worthy, how durable may their joy and felicity be? <hi>Solon</hi> truly sayd; That City was safe whose Citizens were obedient to their Magistrates, and Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strates to their Lawes; what made the Major <hi>Scipio</hi> so victorious, but his wisdom in directing, and his Souldiers willingness in obeying, when he could shew his Troops, and say, You see not a man among all these, but will, if I command him, from a Turret, throw himself into the Sea?</p>
            <p>For obedience to lawful Authority, to Rulers, <note place="margin">Rules &amp; rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons for obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers. <hi>vid. Eccl.</hi> 8. 2, 3, 4.</note> we may find in holy Writ several special Rules, and injunctions, with the reasons thereof, Let e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very soul (none excepted) be subject unto the higher powers; for there is no power but of God, and the powers that be, are ordained of God.</p>
            <p>Second Reason. For he is the Minister of God for thy wealth, to incourage thee in well doing; And he beareth not the sword for nought, for he is the Minister of God to take vengeance on him that doth evil.</p>
            <p>Third Reason. Wherefore ye must be sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, not because of wrath only, but also for conscience sake; not for our own private profit, and advantage, in the enjoying Justice and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venting of injuries, touching our lives, liberties, estates and families, in punishing malefactors, and maintaining our Laws, nor for fear of punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:115181:14"/> but for conscience sake, in duty and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to Gods Ordinance; whereby tis apparent that none can contemn either those Governours or that Government which God hath appointed, without express breach of conscience, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of Gods Ordinance. Here then we find an express divine precept confirmed by a three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold cord of strong Reasons (which cannot easi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be broken) to bind us to obedience. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is subjection and obedience only required, but a further duty also is required; for <hi>for this cause yee pay also tribute, for they are Gods Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters, applying themselves for the same thing, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend the good, and punish the evil.</hi> If Governours doe their duty, spend their spirits, and bestow their pains to protect, maintain and defend our Persons, Laws, Liberties, Lives and Estates, ought not we to doe our duty also, in paying tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute, custome, fear, honour to them? Tribute of true hearts loyalty and faithfulness, Tribute of true and due allegeance; to contribute those customes, duties, rights and privileges which belong to our Governour; also that fear and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence, honour and obedience; filial fear which is due to his Highness as <hi>Pater patriae,</hi> our Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector, nourisher, cherisher and Father of our Country, our Commonwealth. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth <hi>Titus</hi> earnestly to rub up the memory of the people of <hi>Creta,</hi> that they should not forget that good lesson of obedience to <hi>higher powers, Put</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tit. 3. 1.</note>
               <hi>them in remembrance that they be subject to principa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities and powers, and that they be obedient and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to every good work.</hi> And Saint <hi>Peter</hi> with a <note place="margin">2 Pet. 2. 13. &amp;c.</note> sweet compellation, and earnest intreaty, exhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:115181:14"/> the faithful to this not to be neglected duty of obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, <hi>Dearly beloved, I beseech you, submit your selves unto all manner of Ordinance of man, for the Lords sake, whether unto Kings or unto Governours, as unto them that are sent of him, for the punishment of evil doers, and for the praise of them that do well, for so is the will of God, that by well doing ye may put to silence the ignorance of foolish men.</hi> Also prayers and thanksgiving are specially charged by the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postle to be made for all in authority.</p>
            <p>Having shewed the utility and felicity of Obedience, how principally it tendeth to the peace and prosperity of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth, and by divine authority and reasons proved the necessity and benefit of Obedience, and in regard all Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors, Divine, Moral, and Political, are plentiful in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation thereof, and condemnation of the contrary, this point shall briefly be concluded with that saying of <hi>Samuel, 1 Sam.</hi> 15. 22. expressed with an <hi>ecce,</hi> for attentions sake, <hi>Behold! to Obey is better than Sacrifice,</hi> blessed and prosperous, <hi>But Rebellion is as the sin of Witchcraft,</hi> cursed, destructive, and most prejudicial to the peace and safety of all Nations: which in Order leads to the third and last positi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which is this.</p>
            <p>Whosoever resisteth, opposeth, or refuseth submission and obedience to this our present Governour and Government, is a transgressor of Gods Ordinance, and the Laws of the Land, and an Enemy to the publique peace, safety, and prosperity thereof, and deserves exemplary punishment.</p>
            <p>The preceding passages for proof of the two former positions are cleer Testimonies to confirm this present position; yet in regard disobedience to lawful authority is an offence of so high a nature, as that, <hi>numeratur inter scelera jure huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no inexpiabilia,</hi> as tis said <hi>Inter leges Canuti, fol. 118. ca.</hi> 61. That it is numbred among crimes, which by humane lawes are scarcely pardonable, it is requisite to say something thereof. The inconvenience of such stubbornness, that <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sul</hi> knew, who meeting with an obstinate youth, sold both him and his goods, saying. He had no need of that Citizen that would not obey. Now if with an unbyassed Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:115181:15"/> we will speak truth, who can but confess, that we have a Governour compleatly able, fitting, and well-deser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the place God hath bestowed on him: <hi>Criticism</hi> it self cannot find a fault in his Highness justly to cavil at, being both just and merciful.</p>
            <p>Such as love to fish only in troubled waters are fit to catch nothing but <hi>Torpedos,</hi> which poison and kill the takers. That Government can never be safe and settled which is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fested with seditious Sectaries. He that will establish a trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled Government, must first vanquish all his Opposers: Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctious heads must be higher by a pole, than their bodies; for how will the folds be quiet, while yet among them there be some wolves and foxes? He that will rule over many, must fight with many, and conquer, and be sure to cut off those that raise up tumults; or by a majestick aw keep them in a strict subjection. Slackness and connivence are the ruins of unsettled States. Crossing <hi>Corahes,</hi> and seditious <hi>Shebaes,</hi> are such disturbers in all Civil States, that no peace can be expected whilst these Rebells rest unovercome. If they get a head, the Kingdom is divided, so it cannot stand. Separati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are the wounds of a Crown, wherby neglected, it will bleed to death. Such must be subdued, If not cut off yet restrained. It is no cruelty to deny a Traytor liberty: It is no shame, but duty, for subjects to serve; no injury, but Justice, for So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraigns to sway: If it cannot be done without difficulty, Tis better indure a short skirmish, than a long siege; a hard com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate for a happy reign, who would refuse? <hi>Salutaris severitas, beatasecuritas;</hi> That Severity is safe and happy which prevents combustions, and produceth a peaceable se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity. If Christ himself cursed the barren tree, what then shall become of the bad tree that bears no fruit but faction? it must be cut down and cast into the fire; fire brands are fittest to be burnt; let roots that bear Gall and Wormwood be era<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated, <hi>Deut.</hi> 29. 18. 10. Disobedience to Governours, as tis dangerous to the whole State, so it is detestable and dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable in the sight of God, and therefore in his holy word even thoughts of that nature are forbidden, and actions expresly prohibited with a penalty.
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:115181:15"/>
               <hi>In cogitatione tua ne detrahas Regi, &amp;c. quia aves Coeli</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccles. 10. 20.</note>
               <hi>pori abunt vocem tuam, &amp; qui habet pennas annuntiabit sententiam.</hi> Curse not the Ruler, no not in thy thought, &amp;c. <note place="margin">Principi po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puli non ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledices, Thou shalt not speak evil of the Ruler, &amp;c. Ex 22. 28.</note> for the foul of heaven shall carry the voice, and that which hath wings shall declare the matter. Thou canst not so se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly, so closely carry calumny, thy reproach against thy Ruler, but it will be discovered. When the <hi>Israelites</hi> desired a King, and <hi>Saul</hi> by the Lords Judgement (the lot) was elected to that Supreme Authority, those that followed him were said to have their hearts touched by God, and those that despised him were by God termed wicked, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 10. 27. But the wicked men said, how shall he save us? how shall he protect us? so they despisd him, and brought him no presents, And <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. 2. Judgement, damnation, is threatned, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced to the despisers of lawful authority. <hi>There is no power but of God, the powers that be, are ordained of God:</hi> Whosoever therefore resisteth these powers, resisteth the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of God; and they that resist, shall receive to themselves judgement damnation (by some translations) not only punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment among men, but judgement, vengeance from God. <hi>O my soul come not into their secret,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Pro.</hi> 24. 20. Have no Society with the Seditious, for their destruction shall rise suddenly.</p>
            <p>Those Histories in Holy Writ of seditious <hi>Sheba,</hi> &amp; rebellious <hi>Corah,</hi> and his Company, I could wish they might become memorable admonitions and cautionary Examples of heavy Judgements to all the factious firebrands, and mutinous mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>murers of these times, especially to those that profess so much purity and piety, and take upon them (perhaps without <note place="margin">Non mitte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bam prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas et ipsi cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rebant: non lequebar ad eos, et ipsi prophetabant. Jer. 23. 21. vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sionem cordis suil<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> q<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>untur, et non de ore Domini. v. 16.</note> a lawful call thereunto) to become Teachers and Preachers to the people: That if they be Gods Ministers, who is the God of Peace, or the Ambassadors of Jesus Christ, who is the Prince of Peace, or Messengers of the Gospel, which is the Gospel of Peace, they beware that they become not trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets to stir up strife and tumults; That they which should shew the waies of truth and peace, presume not to misconstrue and misapply Texts of holy truth to their own malitious purposes, preach for faith faction, pretend Revelations to raise Rebellions, pick cut parables to affront authority, and
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:115181:16"/> bramble the way of peace: lest the parable of Tares, <hi>Mat.</hi> 13. be properly applyed to them, that sow Tares among wheat, bad and bitter seeds of Sedition, among the wheat of the word of Truth and Peace; lest the pulpit which should be the chair of sound verity, seem to be the chair of insane vanity to vent the frenzied folly of phantastick Brains; lest the pulpit, which hath had the name of the Chair of Truth, become the seat of the scornful, or the stool of iniquity, where falsity and injury are forged for a Law, a place to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vise and publish doctrines of division and dissention, and raise uses tending to Rebellion. God made with the tribe of <hi>Levi</hi> his covenant of life and peace, <hi>Mal.</hi> 2. whose Ministers are those that make a Covenant with Death, and an agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with hell? How beautiful are the feet of those that bring and publish the glad tidings of Peace? saith the Evangelike Prophet <hi>Isaiah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But how severely and sadly do the Prophets, <hi>Jer.</hi> 23. 1. &amp;c. &amp; <hi>Ezek.</hi> 34. 2, 3. &amp;c. denounce woes against those wicked Shepheards that disperse and scatter the Lords flock?</p>
            <p>And now to conclude this third position, It appeareth in the holy Scripture, that seditious and ill-affected persons never prospered, what good soever they pretended, but were alwaies prevented, and were most severely and exemplarily punished, as <hi>Corah, Dathan,</hi> and <hi>Abiram,</hi> in a miraculous manner: <hi>Dirupta est terra sub pedibus eorum, &amp; aperiens os suum devoravit illos, &amp;c.</hi> The earth opened her mouth and swal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed up <hi>Corah</hi> and his company, &amp;c. <hi>Sheba</hi> that seditious <note place="margin">14700. di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of the plague for murmuring a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst Moses, Num. 6. 31, 32. 27. 3. 2 Sa. 10. 1. 22.</note> wretch, stiled therefore a wicked man, because he separated the body from the head, the people from their loyal obedience to their just Ruler, had his head cut off and separated from his Body, and thrown over the Wall of <hi>Abel,</hi> by the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vise of a Woman, who was therefore termed wise, and as a Trumpet was blown to begin, so to end that Rebellion: See how punctually the proportion of the sinne and punishment holds.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Athaliah</hi> the daughter of <hi>Amri, interfecta est gladia,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 King. 11. 16. Ester 12. 2, 3.</note> was slain with the Sword. <hi>Bagathas</hi> and <hi>Thara</hi> against <hi>Assuerus, Appensus est uterque eorum in patibula,</hi>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:115181:16"/> They were examined with torments, and upon confession, put to death. <hi>Absolom</hi> against <hi>David, Suspensus in arbore et Joab infixit tres lanceas in corde ejus,</hi> Hanged in a tree <note place="margin">2 Sam. 18 9.</note> by the hair, between heaven and earth, as unworthy of either, and for his threefold sin, against his God, his King, his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, three darts by <hi>Joab</hi> thrust through his heart. <hi>Achitophel</hi> with <hi>Absolom</hi> against <hi>David,</hi> his counsel turned into foolish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse <note place="margin">2 Sam 17. 23.</note> contemned, <hi>suspensus interiit,</hi> He hanged himself. <hi>Abiathar</hi> the High Priest against <hi>Solomon, Abiathar sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerdoti</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Ki. 2. 26, 27</note>
               <hi>Rex dixit &amp;c. Et quidem vir mortis est,</hi> thou art wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of death, &amp;c. <hi>Ejecit ergo Solomon, ut non esset sacerdos. Shimei</hi> against <hi>David, Gladio interfectus,</hi> slain with the Sword. <hi>Zimri</hi> against <hi>Ela,</hi> who burnt himself. <hi>Theudas,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam 16. 5, 6. 1 Kings 2. 1 Kin. 16. 9. unto the 18. Act 5. 36, 37.</note>
               <hi>(qui occisus est et circitèr 400. qui credebant ei, dispersi sunt et deducti ad nihilum)</hi> And <hi>Judas Galilaeus ipsi perut, et omnes quot quot consenserunt ei, dispersi sunt. Theudas rese</hi> up boarling himself, to whom resorted a number of men, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout 400: who was slain, and they all which obeyed him were scattered and brought to nought. After this man rose up <hi>Judas</hi> of <hi>Galilee,</hi> and drew away much people after him: he also perished, and all that obeyed him were scattered. Lastly <hi>Iudas Iscariot, secundum nomen ejus vir occisionis, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditor proditorum; Et hic quidem possedit agrum de merce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 1. 18. Mat 27 5. la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queo <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e sus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spendit.</note>
               <hi>iniquitatis suae, &amp; suspensus crepuit medius, &amp; diffusa sunt omnia viscera ejus,</hi> According to his name a man of death, Traytor of Traytors; He purchased a Field with the reward of iniquity, and when he had thrown down himself headlong, he burst asunder in the middest, and all his bowels gushed out, and that field called <hi>Aceldama,</hi> the field of blood.</p>
            <p>If we peruse all our Books, Records and Histories, we shall find it a principle in Law, a rule in reason, and a tryall in experience, That Treason, opposition to lawful Government and Authority, doth ever produce fatal and final destruction to the Offenders, ruin is the fruit of Rebellion, and it never attaineth its desired end (Incidents inseparable thereunto) they are not only the instruments of their own destruction, but also the greatest enemies of the publique peace and safety, that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sist
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:115181:17"/> lawful Rulers. <hi>Qui molitur insidias in patriam, id facit quod insanus nauta, perforans navem in qua ipse vehi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur.</hi> Let all men therefore abandon it, as the most poisonous <note place="margin">Faelix quem faciunt aliena pericula can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ium.</note> bait of the devil, the most pernicious plague of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth: And let them follow the precept prescribed in holy Scripture, Fear God, Honour the King, or Chief Magistrate, and have no society with the Seditious, <hi>Prov.</hi> 24. 21. with the firebrands of faction, which conspire and take counsel together against the Lord, and against his annointed, such as clamour, cavil, and carp at lawful Governours, devise and raise scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous rumours, reports, and reproaches against him; whom the Lord hath raised and set over us: from the company of all such rebellious <hi>Corahes,</hi> cursing <hi>Shimeies,</hi> rayling <hi>Rabshekahes,</hi> and seditious <hi>Shebaes,</hi> all wise and vertuous men, honest and godly persons will warily abstain, and carefully refrain; for their end is destruction, they glory in their shame, and their conclusion is confusion.</p>
            <p>But the God of peace, the Prince of peace, the holy Spirit of peace will (maugre all malicious Opposers) send peace up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our <hi>Israel.</hi> And ye that are mindful of the Lord, keep not silence, and give him no rest, until he repair, and until he set up our <hi>Ierusalem,</hi> our Church and Commonwealth the praise of the world, <hi>Isaiah</hi> 62. 7.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>